<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.2.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://0.0.0.0:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://0.0.0.0:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en" /><updated>2025-08-07T12:23:20-05:00</updated><id>http://0.0.0.0:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Ebrahim Khiyami</title><subtitle></subtitle><author><name>Blog Author</name></author><entry><title type="html">AWS Migration and Modernization Experience Day - Dallas</title><link href="http://0.0.0.0:4000/dallas-voc/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="AWS Migration and Modernization Experience Day - Dallas" /><published>2025-07-30T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2025-07-30T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://0.0.0.0:4000/dallas-voc</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://0.0.0.0:4000/dallas-voc/"><![CDATA[<p><img src="/assets/dallas-voc.jpeg" alt="AWS Dallas Event" /></p>

<p>Thanks to the 30+ customers who came to listen to my session last week at the AWS Dallas office for the “AWS Migration and Modernization Experience Day.”</p>

<p>I enjoyed opening up the day with a session about <strong>“Building optimized workloads and making trade-off decisions”</strong>.</p>

<p><a href="https://aws-experience.com/amer/smb/e/84047/migration-and-modernization-experience-day">Event Page</a>
<a href="https://www.linkedin.com/feed/update/urn:li:activity:7355623698227187712/">LinkedIn</a></p>

<h2 id="my-core-message">My Core Message</h2>

<p>Optimizing for cloud is never perfect, so you have to make trade-off decisions. The quality and data you use to make these decisions is what makes the difference in your cloud optimization. This was the theme of my session.</p>

<p>We also touched on some frameworks, automation, and generative AI tools that can help streamline your architecture for AWS best practices and discussed some great questions from the audience.</p>

<h2 id="about-the-event">About the Event</h2>

<p>The AWS Migration and Modernization Experience Day was an intensive learning session designed to elevate organizations’ cloud journey on Amazon Web Services. The roadshow brought together AWS experts and industry practitioners to share operational, optimization, and architectural best practices.</p>

<p>The event covered comprehensive insights spanning:</p>
<ul>
  <li><strong>AWS Well-Architected Framework</strong> best practices for making architectural trade-offs</li>
  <li><strong>Compute and databases</strong> migration and modernization strategies</li>
  <li>How <strong>generative AI (GenAI)</strong> can support the cloud journey</li>
  <li>How to take advantage of <strong>AWS Support teams</strong> and offerings</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="my-session-building-well-architected-workloads">My Session: Building Well-Architected Workloads</h2>

<p>I kicked off the technical sessions with a strategic framework for balancing critical architectural decisions across the five Well-Architected pillars:</p>
<ul>
  <li>Security</li>
  <li>Operational Excellence</li>
  <li>Reliability</li>
  <li>Performance Efficiency</li>
  <li>Cost Optimization</li>
</ul>

<p>The session focused on the reality that cloud optimization isn’t about finding the “perfect” solution—it’s about making informed trade-offs based on quality data and clear business objectives.</p>

<h2 id="key-takeaways">Key Takeaways</h2>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Trade-offs are inevitable</strong> in cloud architecture</li>
  <li><strong>Data quality drives decision quality</strong> in optimization efforts</li>
  <li><strong>Frameworks and automation</strong> can streamline the decision-making process</li>
  <li><strong>Generative AI tools</strong> are becoming valuable allies in architecture optimization</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="event-impact">Event Impact</h2>

<p>The audience engagement was fantastic, with thoughtful questions that showed the real-world challenges teams face when optimizing their cloud workloads. These interactions always remind me why I love working directly with customers—their questions often lead to the best insights.</p>

<p>This type of hands-on, interactive session is exactly what I enjoy most about my role as a Solutions Architect. It’s one thing to build tools and frameworks, but seeing them applied to solve real customer challenges is where the magic happens.</p>

<hr />

<p><em>This session represents the type of customer-facing work I do regularly as part of my role in AWS Cloud Optimization. For more examples of my work, check out my other <a href="/">work samples</a>.</em></p>]]></content><author><name>Ebrahim Khiyami</name></author><category term="media" /><category term="Public Speaking" /><category term="AWS" /><category term="Migration" /><category term="Well-Architected" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Thanks to the 30+ customers who came to listen to my session last week at the AWS Dallas office for the “AWS Migration and Modernization Experience Day.” I enjoyed opening up the day with a session about “Building optimized workloads and making trade-off decisions”. Event Page LinkedIn My Core Message Optimizing for cloud is never perfect, so you have to make trade-off decisions. The quality and data you use to make these decisions is what makes the difference in your cloud optimization. This was the theme of my session. We also touched on some frameworks, automation, and generative AI tools that can help streamline your architecture for AWS best practices and discussed some great questions from the audience. About the Event The AWS Migration and Modernization Experience Day was an intensive learning session designed to elevate organizations’ cloud journey on Amazon Web Services. The roadshow brought together AWS experts and industry practitioners to share operational, optimization, and architectural best practices. The event covered comprehensive insights spanning: AWS Well-Architected Framework best practices for making architectural trade-offs Compute and databases migration and modernization strategies How generative AI (GenAI) can support the cloud journey How to take advantage of AWS Support teams and offerings My Session: Building Well-Architected Workloads I kicked off the technical sessions with a strategic framework for balancing critical architectural decisions across the five Well-Architected pillars: Security Operational Excellence Reliability Performance Efficiency Cost Optimization The session focused on the reality that cloud optimization isn’t about finding the “perfect” solution—it’s about making informed trade-offs based on quality data and clear business objectives. Key Takeaways Trade-offs are inevitable in cloud architecture Data quality drives decision quality in optimization efforts Frameworks and automation can streamline the decision-making process Generative AI tools are becoming valuable allies in architecture optimization Event Impact The audience engagement was fantastic, with thoughtful questions that showed the real-world challenges teams face when optimizing their cloud workloads. These interactions always remind me why I love working directly with customers—their questions often lead to the best insights. This type of hands-on, interactive session is exactly what I enjoy most about my role as a Solutions Architect. It’s one thing to build tools and frameworks, but seeing them applied to solve real customer challenges is where the magic happens. This session represents the type of customer-facing work I do regularly as part of my role in AWS Cloud Optimization. For more examples of my work, check out my other work samples.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">I vibe-coded this webstite completely using Amazon Kiro/Q</title><link href="http://0.0.0.0:4000/built-with-amazon-q/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="I vibe-coded this webstite completely using Amazon Kiro/Q" /><published>2025-07-22T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2025-07-22T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://0.0.0.0:4000/built-with-amazon-q</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://0.0.0.0:4000/built-with-amazon-q/"><![CDATA[<p><img src="/assets/kiro.webp" alt="AWS Kiro" /></p>

<p>I decided to test <a href="https://kiro.dev/">AWS Kiro</a> and Amazon Q Developer to re-build my website, this website. This is to show the capabilities of both tools. I was surprised (and mind blown) at the same time with the ease and simplicity of this process.</p>

<p>I’m not a web developer, but I was still able to live code the entire process that started with taking a basic Jekyll template and keep adding pages, visual components, and other functions to it until I was satisfied with its design. I then connected Kiro with my GitHub account and asked it to publish it to GitHub Pages.</p>

<h2 id="tech-stack">Tech Stack</h2>
<ul>
  <li>Jekyll 4.2.0</li>
  <li>GitHub Pages</li>
  <li>Sass</li>
  <li>Amazon Q CLI</li>
  <li>WebP image optimization</li>
  <li>Git for version control</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="result">Result</h2>
<p>The whole process of migrating from my old github basic  Jekyll template to this one, with better graphic, optimization, and added more functions (for example, my mentoring service), took a few hours. When I finished building everything in my local environment, I asked Q to deploy to production. I did the whole thing. It had some deployment issues initially due to Ruby compatibilities issues with Github Pages, but eventually, it figured out it.</p>

<p>The result is what you see here. A nice website running in production. Let me know what you think.</p>]]></content><author><name>Ebrahim Khiyami</name></author><category term="media" /><category term="Generative AI" /><category term="Solution" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">New hands-on workshop: Accelerate Well-Architected Review using Generative AI</title><link href="http://0.0.0.0:4000/wa-gen-workshop/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="New hands-on workshop: Accelerate Well-Architected Review using Generative AI" /><published>2025-07-22T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2025-07-22T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://0.0.0.0:4000/wa-gen-workshop</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://0.0.0.0:4000/wa-gen-workshop/"><![CDATA[<p><strong>[Deliverable: hands-on workshop + Internal training]</strong>.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/gen-ai-ws.png" alt="Well-Architected Framework" /></p>

<p>This is a hands-on workshop that I built with my team to train customers and internal AWS SAs and account teams on how to use the<a href="https://ekhiyami.github.io/wa-gen-ai/">Well-Architected Review Gen-AI Accelerator</a> that we released a few months ago.</p>

<p>This is a pattern that I usually follow to scale: build something useful, then build a mechanism for other people to use it effectively. In this example, the solution was the IaC Analyzer and the mechanism is this workshop that we built for AWS folks to practice with. We’ve also made it available for our customers who want to train their teams.</p>

<p><strong>This section is taken from my <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/posts/eb-khiyami_accelerate-well-architected-reviews-using-activity-7353858410670379010-H4Zj?utm_source=share&amp;utm_medium=member_desktop&amp;rcm=ACoAAALV-AEByriO-neqsWiP7QcZkthfNqE6-Oo">announcement on LinkedIn</a></strong></p>

<p>Glad to announce the availability of this brand-new hands-on workshop on how to accelerate the <strong>AWS Well-Architected Review process using Generative AI</strong>. We also just completed an internal training for 50 <strong>AWS SAs and TAMs</strong> on using it.</p>

<p>Reach out to your AWS account team (or to me directly) if you’d like to <strong>run this workshop with your team</strong> and learn how Gen AI can accelerate the validation of AWS best practices for your architecture.</p>

<p>This is based on the <a href="https://github.com/aws-samples/aws-well-architected-genai-iac-analyzer">Well-Architected Generative AI Accelerator</a> we released on GitHub a few months ago (IaC Analyzer).</p>

<p>The workshop walks you through the process of deploying the solution and testing it on sample workloads. The tests include validating architecture diagrams, code, and design documents for AWS best practices. It shows you how to complete a full WAR review in minutes (vs. hours using the traditional review process).</p>

<h2 id="access-the-workshop">Access the Workshop</h2>

<p>You can access the workshop here: <a href="https://catalog.workshops.aws/wellarchitected-genai/en-US">Generative AI Accelerator for Well-Architected Review</a></p>]]></content><author><name>Ebrahim Khiyami</name></author><category term="media" /><category term="Generative AI" /><category term="Well-Architected" /><category term="Workshop" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[[Deliverable: hands-on workshop + Internal training].]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Automate the Well-Architected Review w. Amazon Q</title><link href="http://0.0.0.0:4000/automate-wa-review-amazon-q/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Automate the Well-Architected Review w. Amazon Q" /><published>2025-06-15T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2025-06-15T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://0.0.0.0:4000/automate-wa-review-q</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://0.0.0.0:4000/automate-wa-review-amazon-q/"><![CDATA[<p>This blog post was first published on <a href="https://builder.aws.com/content/2wj8D4HmqEjt6wbIBOMVnWx8EOB/automate-the-well-architected-review-w-amazon-q">AWS Builder Center</a></p>

<p><strong>Summary</strong>: This is a summary of the original blog post. For complete details, step-by-step instructions, and full implementation guide, please read the <a href="https://builder.aws.com/content/2wj8D4HmqEjt6wbIBOMVnWx8EOB/automate-the-well-architected-review-w-amazon-q">full article on AWS Builder Center</a>.</p>

<p>Building on my previous work showing how Amazon Q can review draw.io architecture diagrams, this post demonstrates something even more powerful: using Amazon Q to perform a complete Well-Architected Framework Review (WAFR) on Infrastructure as Code templates like CloudFormation or Terraform.</p>

<p>What makes this approach revolutionary is that Amazon Q doesn’t just analyze your architecture—it answers the review questions, identifies risks, and generates a full implementation plan. This transforms a typically 3-4 hour manual process into a 15-minute automated workflow.</p>

<h2 id="what-amazon-q-accomplishes">What Amazon Q Accomplishes</h2>

<ul>
  <li>Iterates through 300+ AWS best practices across all six Well-Architected pillars</li>
  <li>Answers 70+ review questions based on your IaC templates</li>
  <li>Identifies High and Medium Risk Issues (HRIs and MRIs)</li>
  <li>Generates implementation plans for recommended actions</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="the-three-step-process">The Three-Step Process</h2>

<h3 id="step-1-create-a-well-architected-workload">Step 1: Create a Well-Architected Workload</h3>
<p>Set up a workload in the AWS Well-Architected Tool and note its ARN. This becomes the container for your automated review results.</p>

<h3 id="step-2-deploy-your-application">Step 2: Deploy Your Application</h3>
<p>Deploy your application using CloudFormation or Terraform. Amazon Q will analyze this Infrastructure as Code to understand your architecture patterns and configurations.</p>

<h3 id="step-3-run-the-automated-review">Step 3: Run the Automated Review</h3>
<p>Use a carefully crafted prompt to instruct Amazon Q to fetch your template, analyze it against Well-Architected best practices, and populate the review with findings—all automatically.</p>

<h2 id="important-considerations">Important Considerations</h2>

<p>While this automation is powerful, it’s designed to complement, not replace, human expertise. Amazon Q focuses on technical best practices that can be validated through code analysis.</p>

<p>Areas like Operational Excellence—which involve organizational processes, team structures, and cultural practices—still require human insight. The automation gives you a significant head start, but the complete picture needs both technical analysis and human judgment.</p>

<h2 id="real-impact">Real Impact</h2>

<p>In my testing, this approach reduced a typical Well-Architected review from 3-4 hours to just 15 minutes. Amazon Q successfully identified security configurations, reliability patterns, and performance optimizations directly from the CloudFormation template.</p>

<p>The tool is conservative by design—it only marks best practices as “in place” when it finds clear evidence in your code. This ensures accuracy while providing a solid foundation for deeper architectural discussions.</p>

<h2 id="whats-next">What’s Next</h2>

<p>This approach opens doors to domain-specific reviews using additional lenses from the AWS Lens Catalog—like Containers, Serverless, or industry-specific frameworks. The automation scales to handle complex, multi-service architectures while maintaining consistency across reviews.</p>

<p>This represents a fundamental shift in how we approach architecture reviews—from manual, time-intensive processes to automated, consistent, and scalable assessments that free up architects to focus on strategic decisions rather than checklist validation.</p>]]></content><author><name>Blog Author</name></author><category term="media" /><category term="Generative AI" /><category term="Well-Architected" /><category term="Automation" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[This blog post was first published on AWS Builder Center Summary: This is a summary of the original blog post. For complete details, step-by-step instructions, and full implementation guide, please read the full article on AWS Builder Center. Building on my previous work showing how Amazon Q can review draw.io architecture diagrams, this post demonstrates something even more powerful: using Amazon Q to perform a complete Well-Architected Framework Review (WAFR) on Infrastructure as Code templates like CloudFormation or Terraform. What makes this approach revolutionary is that Amazon Q doesn’t just analyze your architecture—it answers the review questions, identifies risks, and generates a full implementation plan. This transforms a typically 3-4 hour manual process into a 15-minute automated workflow. What Amazon Q Accomplishes Iterates through 300+ AWS best practices across all six Well-Architected pillars Answers 70+ review questions based on your IaC templates Identifies High and Medium Risk Issues (HRIs and MRIs) Generates implementation plans for recommended actions The Three-Step Process Step 1: Create a Well-Architected Workload Set up a workload in the AWS Well-Architected Tool and note its ARN. This becomes the container for your automated review results. Step 2: Deploy Your Application Deploy your application using CloudFormation or Terraform. Amazon Q will analyze this Infrastructure as Code to understand your architecture patterns and configurations. Step 3: Run the Automated Review Use a carefully crafted prompt to instruct Amazon Q to fetch your template, analyze it against Well-Architected best practices, and populate the review with findings—all automatically. Important Considerations While this automation is powerful, it’s designed to complement, not replace, human expertise. Amazon Q focuses on technical best practices that can be validated through code analysis. Areas like Operational Excellence—which involve organizational processes, team structures, and cultural practices—still require human insight. The automation gives you a significant head start, but the complete picture needs both technical analysis and human judgment. Real Impact In my testing, this approach reduced a typical Well-Architected review from 3-4 hours to just 15 minutes. Amazon Q successfully identified security configurations, reliability patterns, and performance optimizations directly from the CloudFormation template. The tool is conservative by design—it only marks best practices as “in place” when it finds clear evidence in your code. This ensures accuracy while providing a solid foundation for deeper architectural discussions. What’s Next This approach opens doors to domain-specific reviews using additional lenses from the AWS Lens Catalog—like Containers, Serverless, or industry-specific frameworks. The automation scales to handle complex, multi-service architectures while maintaining consistency across reviews. This represents a fundamental shift in how we approach architecture reviews—from manual, time-intensive processes to automated, consistent, and scalable assessments that free up architects to focus on strategic decisions rather than checklist validation.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Chat with your AWS bill using AWS MCP, Amazon Q CLI</title><link href="http://0.0.0.0:4000/chat-with-aws/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Chat with your AWS bill using AWS MCP, Amazon Q CLI" /><published>2025-05-06T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2025-05-06T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://0.0.0.0:4000/chat-with-aws</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://0.0.0.0:4000/chat-with-aws/"><![CDATA[<p>This blog post was first published on <a href="https://community.aws/editor/posts/edit/content/2mIzefdB2B2g94f3YxoxkVObuTo?v=2wjQFa02dCwNzdevZPZIy9nplr4">AWS Community</a></p>

<p># Chat with Your AWS Bill Using Amazon Q CLI</p>

<p>In this blog post, I’ll walk you through a simple demo to chat with your AWS bill—break it down, analyze it, and get cost optimization recommendations based on the AWS Well-Architected best practices. This uses the latest <strong>MCP support</strong> recently added to the <strong>Amazon Q CLI</strong>.</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="-what-can-you-ask">💬 What can you ask?</h2>

<p>With this setup, you can ask Amazon Q natural language questions like:</p>

<ul>
  <li>What is my storage cost across all regions?</li>
  <li>What is my total spend in the last month?</li>
  <li>Based on my S3 usage, can you recommend ways to reduce costs?</li>
  <li>…and much more.</li>
</ul>

<p>Amazon Q will understand your question using one MCP server, then route it to another server that can fetch and calculate the data. In some cases, it may even generate and run scripts on your behalf to get the answer. For example, if you ask for the <strong>total cost of EBS storage across all regions</strong>, it may need to gather and compute data that’s not directly available from the Cost Explorer API.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=dQw4w9WgXcQ" title="Watch the Demo">
  <img src="/assets/yt.png" alt="Watch the video" width="40" />
</a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=dQw4w9WgXcQ">Watch the demo</a></p>

<hr />

<p><strong>The architecture is a standard MCP server architecture</strong>.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/chat-bill.png" alt="chat-bill" /></p>

<hr />

<h2 id="-the-setup-is-simple">🧱 The setup is simple</h2>

<h3 id="step-1-set-up-amazon-q-cli">Step 1: Set up Amazon Q CLI</h3>

<ul>
  <li>Install the Amazon Q CLI</li>
  <li>Run <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">q login</code></li>
  <li>Run <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">q chat</code></li>
</ul>

<h3 id="️-step-2-configure-mcp-servers">⚙️ Step 2: Configure MCP servers</h3>

<p>To enable cost optimization queries, you need to link Amazon Q with the correct MCP servers. Do this by editing (or creating) the following file:</p>

<p>```bash
~/.aws/amazonq/mcp.json</p>

<p>Paste the following configuration:</p>

<p>{
  “mcpServers”: {
    “awslabs.core-mcp-server”: {
      “command”: “/Users/ekhiyami/.local/bin/uvx”,
      “args”: [“awslabs.core-mcp-server@latest”],
      “env”: {
        “FASTMCP_LOG_LEVEL”: “ERROR”
      },
      “autoApprove”: [“prompt_understanding”],
      “disabled”: false
    },
    “awslabs.cost-analysis-mcp-server”: {
      “command”: “/Users/ekhiyami/.local/bin/uvx”,
      “args”: [“awslabs.cost-analysis-mcp-server@latest”],
      “env”: {
        “FASTMCP_LOG_LEVEL”: “ERROR”,
        “AWS_PROFILE”: “default”
      },
      “autoApprove”: [“analyze_cdk_project”]
    }
  }
}</p>

<p>Restart your session and start asking questions about your AWS spend. Check the video above for examples.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.linkedin.com/posts/eb-khiyami_chat-with-your-aws-bill-activity-7325533983788662786-PT-6?utm_source=share&amp;utm_medium=member_desktop&amp;rcm=ACoAAALV-AEByriO-neqsWiP7QcZkthfNqE6-Oo">LinkedIn Post</a></p>

<p><img src="/assets/chatbill.png" alt="chatbill" /></p>

<h2 id="-helpful-resources">🔗 Helpful Resources</h2>

<ul>
  <li><a href="https://github.com/aws-samples/amazon-q-mcp-servers">List of all AWS MCP servers</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://docs.aws.amazon.com/q/developer-guide/getting-started-cli.html">Amazon Q Installation Guide</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://github.com/aws-samples/amazon-q-cli">Amazon Q MCP Integration</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://github.com/aws-samples/amazon-q-mcp-cost-analysis">Cost Analysis MCP Server</a></li>
</ul>]]></content><author><name>Blog Author</name></author><category term="media" /><category term="Generative AI" /><category term="Solution" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[This blog post was first published on AWS Community]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">New Digital Course: AWS Well-Architected for Enterprise</title><link href="http://0.0.0.0:4000/wa-enterprise/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="New Digital Course: AWS Well-Architected for Enterprise" /><published>2025-02-15T00:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2025-02-15T00:00:00-06:00</updated><id>http://0.0.0.0:4000/wa-enterprise</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://0.0.0.0:4000/wa-enterprise/"><![CDATA[<p><strong>[Deliverable: AWS Training &amp; Certifications Digital Course Available for Customers, Partners, and Field, Blog Post]</strong></p>

<p><strong>Short Summary</strong></p>

<p>This is my latest publication. After publishing the <a href="https://ekhiyami.github.io/wa-course/">Well-Architected Foundation digital course</a> last year and making it available for AWS customers and partners, I received feedback that the course is basic and doesn’t go into the details and advanced options. So, I took the lead on creating an advanced version of it. We called it <strong>Well-Architected for Enterprises</strong>. As the name implies, it’s designed to teach our customers how to do scale adoption of best practices for 100s of applications and show them what tools, programs, solutions available for them to do so.</p>

<p>The course took about <strong>6 months</strong> to complete, including planning, assembling a team of SMEs and reviewers, creating the content, and developing knowledge checks. At the time of writing this post, the course has received <strong>positive feedback</strong> and has been taken by about <strong>5k individuals</strong>.</p>

<hr />

<p><strong>Course Description</strong></p>

<p>The course covers best practices for:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Preparing and running <strong>Well-Architected Framework Reviews (WAFR)</strong>.</li>
  <li>Providing <strong>interactive scenarios</strong> to identify and remediate architecture risks.</li>
  <li>Offering <strong>recommendations</strong> for building scalable mechanisms to use the Well-Architected Framework across multiple workloads and teams.</li>
</ul>

<p>It also covers key tools, resources, and programs such as:</p>

<ul>
  <li><a href="https://aws.amazon.com/well-architected-tool/">AWS Well-Architected Tool</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://aws.amazon.com/well-architected/lenses/">AWS Well-Architected Lenses</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://aws.amazon.com/partners/well-architected/">AWS Well-Architected Partner Program</a></li>
</ul>

<p>Furthermore, it explores how <strong>generative AI</strong> can be used to scale and streamline WAFRs.</p>

<p><strong>What Does the Course Teach You?</strong></p>

<p>✅ <strong>AWS Well-Architected Foundations</strong>
The course begins with a review of the <strong>core elements</strong> of the Well-Architected Framework, including its <strong>pillars</strong>, <strong>design principles</strong>, and <strong>best practices</strong>. This section ensures a <strong>strong foundation</strong> for advanced topics.</p>

<p>✅ <strong>How to Prepare and Run a Well-Architected Framework Review</strong>
You’ll learn how to:</p>
<ul>
  <li>Identify workloads.</li>
  <li>Maximize the value of the review through interactive scenarios and example workloads.</li>
  <li>Use AWS tools like <strong>Trusted Advisor</strong> and <strong>Service Screener</strong> to enhance the review process.</li>
</ul>

<p>✅ <strong>How to Improve Workload Architecture</strong>
Learn to identify <strong>architecture risks</strong>, prioritize them based on <strong>business goals</strong>, and develop <strong>remediation plans</strong> with recommended timelines.</p>

<p>✅ <strong>How to Scale Across Large Organizations</strong>
Discover mechanisms for <strong>standardizing processes</strong>, improving <strong>organizational visibility</strong>, and leveraging AWS tools for <strong>efficient adoption</strong> of Well-Architected best practices.</p>

<p>✅ <strong>How to Leverage Generative AI</strong>
Learn how <strong>generative AI</strong> can optimize and automate parts of WAFR, saving <strong>time</strong> and <strong>resources</strong> as your organization scales.</p>

<p><strong>Launch Materials</strong></p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://aws.amazon.com/blogs/training-and-certification/well-architected-for-enterprises/">Announcement Blog Post on AWS Training &amp; Certification Blog</a></p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://explore.skillbuilder.aws/learn/courses/21868/well-architected-for-enterprises/lessons">Well-Architected for Enterprises Digital Course</a></p>
  </li>
</ul>

<hr />

<p><img src="/assets/wa-enterprise.png" alt="wa-gen-ai" /></p>]]></content><author><name>Blog Author</name></author><category term="media" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[[Deliverable: AWS Training &amp; Certifications Digital Course Available for Customers, Partners, and Field, Blog Post]]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Gen-AI Assisted AWS Well-Architected Review</title><link href="http://0.0.0.0:4000/wa-gen-ai/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Gen-AI Assisted AWS Well-Architected Review" /><published>2024-10-23T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2024-10-23T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://0.0.0.0:4000/wa-gen-ai</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://0.0.0.0:4000/wa-gen-ai/"><![CDATA[<p><strong>[Deliverable: re:Invent2024 session, customer case study, AWS Sample Solution and more]</strong>.</p>

<p><strong>Short Summary</strong></p>

<p>This is WA-Gen-AI app. My second Gen-AI POC that I built this year after the success I had in building the first one, the <a href="https://ekhiyami.github.io/video-chat/">YouTube Summarizer</a>.</p>

<p>In this POC, I use Gen-AI to streamline the Well-Architected Review for an application written in Infrastructure as Code (IaC), e.g., CloudFormation, Terraform, or else.</p>

<p>This solutions received a lot of attractrions from my collegues and from AWS customers. 
After I published I was reached out by an awesome group of SAs in my team who took it and improve it and went through the necessary reviews to make it an offical solutiosn on AWS Repo.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/wagenai-2.png" alt="wa-gen-ai" /></p>

<p>In recent weeks, <strong>Commonwealth Bank</strong>, an Australian multinational bank, used this solution to streamline their Well-Architected Reviews.</p>

<p>They were so impressed that they wanted to showcase it publicly on stage at <strong>re:Invent 2024</strong>, AWS’s largest annual conference.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><strong>You can try my personal version <a href="https://wa-genai.streamlit.app/">here</a>.</strong>
<strong>Check my blog post on AWS Community <a href="https://community.aws/content/2hYteYyGPff8nuzG3ye8HZQOtCf/how-i-cut-the-time-to-complete-a-well-architected-review-from-hours-to-minutes?lang=en">here</a></strong></p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <p><strong><a href="https://github.com/aws-samples/well-architected-iac-analyzer">This is the the official version from AWS Sample</a>.</strong></p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <p><strong>You can watch the demonstation on re:Invent stage <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=1DUIwJfNvKg">here</a>.</strong></p>
</blockquote>

<p><strong>Long Summary</strong></p>

<p>If you’ve been an AWS customer for some time you should be familiar with the <a href="https://docs.aws.amazon.com/wellarchitected/latest/framework/welcome.html">Well-Architected Framework</a> . It’s the ultimate collection of AWS best practices across 6 pillars (Operational Excellence, Security, Reliability, Performance Efficiency, Cost Optimization, and Sustainability).</p>

<p>and the <strong>Well-Architected Review</strong>  is the process to validate your architecture for these best practices. The results would be a list of identified risks (high, medium) in the architecture and action items to improve them.</p>

<p>The <strong>WA-Gen-AI App</strong> takes a CloudFormation template uploaded by the user, uses AWS Bedrock for Gen-AI and Streamlit for the front-end, and Python to interact with the AWS Well-Architected Tool, iterate through best practices, and complete the review.</p>

<hr />

<p>In my testing, I was able to complete the review in a few minutes, compared with a few hours that were traditionally needed by customers or the AWS team to bring everyone into the same room and answer the 57 of review questions manually.</p>

<p>In the 3-tier classic application I tested, the WA-Gen-AI app was able to answer about <strong>50%</strong> of the questions and save <strong>hours</strong> of manual review.</p>

<hr />

<h3 id="more-details">More details</h3>

<ul>
  <li>[AWS re:Invent 2024 - Building an optimized cloud workload with AWS (SUP201)](<a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=1DUIwJfNvKg">https://youtu.be/agTKnB1PS2M</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://community.aws/content/2hYteYyGPff8nuzG3ye8HZQOtCf/how-i-cut-the-time-to-complete-a-well-architected-review-from-hours-to-minutes?lang=en">Blog post with architecture and technical details</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://youtu.be/agTKnB1PS2M">Video Demo</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://github.com/ekhiyami/well-architected-genai">Github Repo (personal)</a></li>
  <li>What People Say <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/posts/eb-khiyami_how-i-cut-the-time-to-complete-a-well-architected-activity-7242641906160050176-Dz1L?utm_source=share&amp;utm_medium=member_desktop">LinkedIn Post</a></li>
</ul>

<hr />

<p><img src="/assets/wa-genai-post.png" alt="wa-gen-ai-post" /></p>]]></content><author><name>Blog Author</name></author><category term="media" /><category term="Generative AI" /><category term="Best Practices" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[[Deliverable: re:Invent2024 session, customer case study, AWS Sample Solution and more].]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">FutureIT Dallas Summit</title><link href="http://0.0.0.0:4000/idc-dallas/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="FutureIT Dallas Summit" /><published>2024-10-15T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2024-10-15T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://0.0.0.0:4000/idc-dallas</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://0.0.0.0:4000/idc-dallas/"><![CDATA[<p>I recently had the opportunity to represent AWS at the <a href="https://event.ciofutureit.com/futureit-dallas/">FutureIT2024 Dallas</a> conference held at AT&amp;T Stadium. This is a significant networking event in the Dallas metro area, attended by 200+ IT and security executives and professionals, including managers, directors, VPs, CIOs, and other industry leaders.</p>

<p>This year’s theme was <strong>Data, AI, and Digital Innovation: Preparing for Emerging Technologies in Business and Building Trust with Customers and Internally.</strong></p>

<p>During the event, I led an in-depth <strong>table discussion</strong>, along with my partners from Rackspace and MontyCloud, titled <strong>Overcoming Obstacles in Your Cloud Journey with AWS</strong>,</p>

<p>Additionally, I <strong>presented a session titled “Proactive Cloud Management: How to Fill in the Gaps.</strong> The session addressed common challenges customers face when scaling their cloud operations and highlighted how the AWS Cloud Optimization team helps resolve these challenges, using real-world examples.</p>

<p>The event was well-received, with positive feedback on the session, particularly for the practical examples discussed on creating Cloud Operations Centers at scale, such as those at Fidelity and Cox Automotive using the Well-Architected framework.</p>

<p><a href="https://event.ciofutureit.com/futureit-dallas/">EventLink</a></p>

<p><a href="https://event.ciofutureit.com/futureit-dallas/futureit-dallas-2024-meet-our-expert-speakers/">Speakers</a></p>

<hr />

<p><img src="/assets/idc2.jpeg" alt="idc2" /></p>]]></content><author><name>Blog Author</name></author><category term="media" /><category term="Public Speaking" /><category term="Optimization" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I recently had the opportunity to represent AWS at the FutureIT2024 Dallas conference held at AT&amp;T Stadium. This is a significant networking event in the Dallas metro area, attended by 200+ IT and security executives and professionals, including managers, directors, VPs, CIOs, and other industry leaders.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">My YouTube Summarizer that Went Viral</title><link href="http://0.0.0.0:4000/video-chat/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="My YouTube Summarizer that Went Viral" /><published>2024-06-10T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2024-06-10T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://0.0.0.0:4000/video-chat</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://0.0.0.0:4000/video-chat/"><![CDATA[<p><strong>[Deliverable: YouTube Summarizer, blog post, more].</strong></p>

<p>As part of learning Gen AI, I built an app that ‘summarizes YouTube videos and makes them conversational’.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><strong>You can try it <a href="https://video-chat.streamlit.app/">here</a>.</strong></p>
</blockquote>

<p><img src="/assets/video-chat.png" alt="Video Chat App" /></p>

<p>The whole process from starting building the code to writing a blog post about it took about 6 hours. The app was received with celebration by the community and many VPs at AWS because it shows how efficiently you can be to build quick products that solve real problems using AWS Gen AI Stack.</p>

<p>To date, the app has been used by more than <strong>*100k</strong> users. Wow, beyond my expectation. Maybe I should build a commercial version?</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p>My blog post on how I built and a demo it is on the <a href="https://community.aws/content/2hPtf0UuIXSLqJk5MKolbOoA7Qv/how-i-built-a-video-chatter-app-with-almost-zero-code?lang=en">AWS Community Blog</a>.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>My LinkedIn <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/eb-khiyami/recent-activity/all/">Post</a> about the story with references.</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<hr />

<h3 id="whats-next">What’s next</h3>

<p>The app is being utlized by multiple teams internally and i’m working on adding more features to it for traslations and support of languages other than English. There is alos something public coming about it..can’t disclose this one yet.</p>

<h3 id="what-people-say-about-it">What people say about it</h3>

<p><strong>Matt Wood (VP of AI Products, AWS)</strong></p>

<p><img src="/assets/video-chat-matt.png" alt="Video Chat App" /></p>

<p><strong>Swami SivasubramanianSwami Sivasubramanian (VP, AI and Data, AWS)</strong></p>

<p><img src="/assets/video-chat-swami.png" alt="Video Chat App" /></p>

<p><strong>Jeff Barr (VP, Chief Evangelist, AWS)</strong></p>

<p><img src="/assets/video-chat-jeff.png" alt="Video Chat App" /></p>]]></content><author><name>Blog Author</name></author><category term="Generative AI" /><category term="POC" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[[Deliverable: YouTube Summarizer, blog post, more]. As part of learning Gen AI, I built an app that ‘summarizes YouTube videos and makes them conversational’. You can try it here.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Disaster Recovery for Azure/GCP on AWS</title><link href="http://0.0.0.0:4000/dr/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Disaster Recovery for Azure/GCP on AWS" /><published>2024-05-01T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2024-05-01T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://0.0.0.0:4000/dr</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://0.0.0.0:4000/dr/"><![CDATA[<p><strong>[Deliverable: AWS Service, 6 blog posts, AWS Sample Solution, AWS Documentation].</strong></p>

<blockquote>
  <p>I built a solution to set up Disaster Recovery sites on AWS for Azure and GCP customers. After being used successfully by multiple customers and translated into multiple languages as blog posts, the solution became part of the official AWS Disaster Recovery Service (AWS DRS).</p>
</blockquote>

<h3 id="here-is-the-full-story">Here is the full story</h3>

<p>Last year, I took on a new challenge to expand my technical impact by joining the Resilience Technical Field Community (TFC) at AWS as a Disaster Recovery SME. This role complemented my work on the Well-Architected team, where I engaged with several customers whose main workloads were on Azure or GCP. These customers wanted to leverage AWS Disaster Recovery Service (AWS DRS) to build a disaster recovery solution on AWS.</p>

<p>During my interactions, I discovered a significant gap in the AWS Disaster Recovery Service (AWS DRS) failback process (from AWS to GCP/Azure). The failback client provided by AWS DRS was not directly compatible with booting on Azure/GCP VMs. Many customers had to manually build a custom image on EC2 with the failback client before creating a compatible VM on the respective cloud.</p>

<hr />

<blockquote>
  <p>In a DR solution, there are two main steps: <strong>failover</strong>, which is to fail from a primary site to your backup site in case of a disaster, and <strong>failback</strong>, which is the opposite operation, to fail back from the backup site to the main site after the disaster situation is cleared.</p>
</blockquote>

<hr />

<p>To address this issue, I developed a solution to automate the steps needed to build an Azure/GCP-compatible VM with AWS DRS, ready to boot from. I collaborated with the head of product at AWS DRS to get my solution approved and published it on <strong><a href="https://github.com/aws-samples">AWS Samples</a></strong> (an official AWS repo for sample solutions approved by AWS, ready for customers to use). This solution included automation scripts that both Azure and GCP customers could use to streamline the failback process while building their DR on AWS.</p>

<p>To help the community, I also wrote a series of blog posts titled <strong>Building a Disaster Recovery Site on AWS for Multi-cloud Workloads</strong> providing a step-by-step implementation guide. Since releasing these solutions, they have helped numerous customers unblock their DR projects on AWS. It also assisted the <strong>AWS Support</strong> team in resolving multiple SIMs and contributed to progressing <strong>SFDC opportunities</strong>, generating significant <strong>ARR</strong>. The blog posts have been <strong>recognized</strong> by my colleagues at AWS for their improtance and were <strong>translated</strong> to Spanish and Japanees.</p>

<h2 id="here-is-what-i-delivered">Here is what I delivered</h2>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://github.com/aws-samples/aws-drs-failback-client-azure-gcp">The Solutions on AWS Sample</a></p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>The Blog Posts Series</strong></p>

    <ul>
      <li><a href="https://aws.amazon.com/jp/blogs/news/building-a-disaster-recovery-site-on-aws-for-workloads-on-google-cloud-part-1/">Building a disaster recovery site on AWS for workloads on Google Cloud Part 1 (Japanese)</a></li>
      <li><a href="https://aws.amazon.com/jp/blogs/news/building-a-disaster-recovery-site-on-aws-for-workloads-on-google-cloud-part-2/">Building a disaster recovery site on AWS for workloads on Google Cloud Part 1 (Japanese)</a></li>
      <li><a href="https://aws.amazon.com/blogs/storage/building-a-disaster-recovery-site-on-aws-for-workloads-on-google-cloud-part-2/">Building a disaster recovery site on AWS for workloads on Google Cloud Part 2</a></li>
      <li><a href="https://aws.amazon.com/blogs/storage/building-a-disaster-recovery-site-on-aws-for-workloads-on-google-cloud-part-1/">Building a disaster recovery site on AWS for workloads on Google Cloud Part 1</a></li>
      <li><a href="https://aws.amazon.com/es/blogs/aws-spanish/configurando-un-plan-de-recuperacion-de-desastres-drp-entre-aws-y-azure-utilizando-cloudendure/">Configurando un plan de recuperación de desastres (DRP) entre AWS y Azure utilizando CloudEndure (Spanish)</a></li>
      <li><a href="https://aws.amazon.com/blogs/architecture/field-notes-building-a-disaster-recovery-site-on-aws-for-your-azure-workload/">Field Notes: Building a Disaster Recovery site on AWS for your Azure Workload</a></li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>That became part of AWS DRS Documentation</strong></p>
    <ul>
      <li><a href="https://docs.aws.amazon.com/drs/latest/userguide/failback-performing-main.html">AWS Disaster Recovery Service - Performing a Failback</a></li>
    </ul>
  </li>
</ul>

<h2 id="what-people-say-about-it">What people say about it</h2>

<p><img src="/assets/dr.png" alt="dr" /></p>]]></content><author><name>Blog Author</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[[Deliverable: AWS Service, 6 blog posts, AWS Sample Solution, AWS Documentation]. I built a solution to set up Disaster Recovery sites on AWS for Azure and GCP customers. After being used successfully by multiple customers and translated into multiple languages as blog posts, the solution became part of the official AWS Disaster Recovery Service (AWS DRS). Here is the full story Last year, I took on a new challenge to expand my technical impact by joining the Resilience Technical Field Community (TFC) at AWS as a Disaster Recovery SME. This role complemented my work on the Well-Architected team, where I engaged with several customers whose main workloads were on Azure or GCP. These customers wanted to leverage AWS Disaster Recovery Service (AWS DRS) to build a disaster recovery solution on AWS. During my interactions, I discovered a significant gap in the AWS Disaster Recovery Service (AWS DRS) failback process (from AWS to GCP/Azure). The failback client provided by AWS DRS was not directly compatible with booting on Azure/GCP VMs. Many customers had to manually build a custom image on EC2 with the failback client before creating a compatible VM on the respective cloud.]]></summary></entry></feed>